<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	HA-JDBC: High-Availability JDBC
	Copyright (C) 2012  Paul Ferraro
	
	This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
	the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
	(at your option) any later version.

	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

	You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
	along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-changes-plugin/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>HA-JDBC Changes</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="3.0.3" date="2014-07-25">
			<action type="fix" due-to="Justin Cranford">
				Avoid use of PreparedStatement.addBatch(String) in SQLStateManager since not all dialects support it.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Add ability to override the default logical address of the JGroups channel.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix alter sequence SQL for Oracle dialect.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix NPE when previous coordinator is restarted.
				Refactor command dispatcher logic using channel that does not discard its own messages.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix MySQL restore process - replace file pipe with writing file directly to the process output.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure ProcessBuilder.environment() uses prileged action.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Use INVOKE_ON_ANY strategy for Connection.getTransactionIsolation() - most drivers don't require a round trip to the database for this.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix bug in DistributedStateManager where our local state is never persisted during activation/deactivation.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Add support for data-only dump-restore.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Don't deactivate local databases on stop until we can distinguish between embedded databases and local databases using separate processes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure that we rollback any current transactions to release any locks before closing the connections to an inactive database.
				This is necessary if the connection is pooled.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix alter sequence SQL for Oracle dialect.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="3.0.2" date="2014-04-07">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix NoClassDefFoundError in SLF4J and Commons logging providers when the requisite classes are not available.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="3.0.1" date="2014-04-03">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to 3.4.3.Final
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactor DumpRestoreSupport to support dialects that do not require external process execution.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure Database.setActive(...) is set correctly during startup.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixes issue where DataSource is created multiple times, which is very bad if the DataSource encapsulates a connection pool.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix table introspection in Oracle dialect to use user name as schema.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix failure detection logic in H2 and HSQLDB dialects.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix dump/restore in MySQL dialect to use -r option.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Improve resiliency of invocation strategies to concurrent database deactivation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Distributable state manager needs to delegate to local state manager on activate/deactivate.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix issue where HA-JDBC proxies can retain stale references to objects from a deactivated database if that database is reactivated before being accessed.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="3.0.0" date="2013-12-30">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Update default jgroups configuration.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="3.0.0-rc-1" date="2013-11-06">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Re-versioned to 3.0.  The scope of changes since 2.0.x justifies a major release bump.
			</action>
			<action type="update" due-to="sjones4">
				Add option to drop PostgreSQL database object before restoring.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" due-to="sjones4">
				Fix input channel registration.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed UnsupportedOperationException when using dump-restore sync strategy due to incorrect regex parsing of jdbc url.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" due-to="sjones4">
				Allow runtime change to weight for active databases.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to 3.4.0.Final.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.0-beta-4" date="2013-08-11">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to 3.3.x.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Optimize SynchronousExecutor.invokeAll(...) and make sure reverse mode doesn't execute first task until all other tasks are complete.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Make DatabaseCluster references within HA-JDBC driver static.  Fixes integration with Tomcat connection pooling.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Deactivate all local active databases upon DatabaseCluster.stop().
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				If DatabaseCluster fails to start, stop it before clearing its reference from the Registry.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Add Dialect.isValid(Connection) to allow workaround for dialects that do not implement Connection.isValid(int).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Don't create a proxy for null results, e.g. ResultSet.getClob(...).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Use a new TreeMap to store results, not an immutable singleton map.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed parsing bug in Driver.getMajorVersion()/getMinorVersion() that prevented deployment on JBoss AS7.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Allow DataSource Reference to define config using URI (not just serialized form).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Add support for Blob.setBinaryStream(long), Clob.setAsciiStream(long) and Clob.setCharacterStream(long) via OutputStream and Writer, respectively.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Add "input-sink" configuration property to control whether InputStream and Reader-based update methods will use a file or in-memory sink.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				When loading service providers, skip providers with missing dependencies.  This way optional dependencies are truly optional.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				REPEATABLE_READ queries should execute against primary database only.
			</action>
			<action due-to="sjones4" type="fix">
				Avoid classpath scan per exception, due to use of ServiceLoader to resolve exception types.
			</action>
			<action due-to="sjones4" type="fix">
				Fix improper unlock logic in LocalTransactionContext which could preventing database activation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Correct reserved identifier logic to only include SQL:2003 reserved words by default.
				Add explicit reserved identifier overrides for PostgreSQL and MySQL.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.0-beta-3" date="2012-12-09">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Switch default durability from "fine" to "coarse".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Restore ability to add new databases to the cluster at runtime via JMX.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure event source field is not lost during serialization.
			</action>
			<action due-to="eskorzeny" type="fix">
				Fix configuration file location on windows when file path contains spaces.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Add debug logging if Connection.isValid(...) throws an exception.
				Otherwise, it is difficult to debug connectivity issues when connection pooling is used.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"" issue="2">
				Complete BerkeleyDB state manager implementation.
			</action>
			<action due-to="eskorzeny" type="fix">
				Always flush the output stream during state transfer.
			</action>
			<action due-to="eskorzeny" type="fix">
				Fix class name of JGroupsCommandDispatcherFactory within META-INF/services/net.sf.hajdbc.distributed.CommandDispatcherFactory.
			</action>
			<action due-to="eskorzeny" type="update">
				Rename SimpleStateManagerFactory from "memory" to "simple".
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to 3.2.4.Final.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				XML parser should fail if dialect/durability/balancer/meta-data-cache was not found.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix formatting of JBoss Logging messages.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="5">
				Auto-activation and auto-deactivation only need to be triggered on the group coordinator.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Drop obsolete Dialect.getSimpleSQL().
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.0-beta-2" date="2012-10-27">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"" issue="3">
				Complete SQLite state manager implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Relocate default location of SQL state manager databases to $HOME/.ha-jdbc
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix xml parsing of pooling configuration for state managers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix recovery query logic in SQL state manager.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix NPE in MulitplexingDecoderFactory if password is null.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix dialect detection in SQL state manager.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Drop deprecated properties from default jgroups configuration.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix HSQLDB Dialect.getDefaultSchemas() to return "PUBLIC".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Database meta data cache should store table/schema names quoted, if necessary.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Allow override of identifier normalization by refactoring DatabaseMetaDataSupport into Dialect interface.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade Mockito to version 1.9.5.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to version 3.2.0.Final.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.1.0-beta-1" date="2012-10-11">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrate source code repository to github.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Update Java runtime requirement to 1.6.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Update Java compile requirement to 1.7 (for JDBC 4.1 support).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrate build from Ant to Maven.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrate site generation from Forrest to Maven site plugin.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replace JiBX with JAXB for configuration file reading/writing.
				Configuration schema is now auto-generated from annotations during build.
				XML parsing will validate against the schema.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Redesign HA-JDBC startup, adding support for programmatic configuration.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Store references to database clusters within Driver or DataSource object, rather than in the mbean server.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replace mbean interfaces with dynamic mbeans created from annotations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replace java.util.prefs-based state manager with a jdbc-based or in-memory implementation.
				Add alternative implementations for sqlite (via sqljet) and berkeleydb.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Add generic pooling mechanism for use by state managers.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Add ability to obfuscate passwords stored in HA-JDBC configuration file.
				Supported mechanisms: plain text, hex encoding, base-64 encoding, symmetric encryption.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Add support for version (e.g. last update timestamp) columns to differential sync strategy.
				This improves the general performance of change detection from O(N*M) -> O(N), where N is number of rows, and M is number of columns.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed failure detection handling to always prefer response from the designated primary database (instead of always preferring successful responses).
				Apply the same logic to resolve jdbc method result conflicts.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Add durability support to detect and recover from node crashes during commit, enabled by default.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Improve reliability of distributed lock manager by locking coordinator first, then broadcasting lock acquisition event to other members.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Use exception introspection to determine whether a not a given failure is catastrophic, replacing separate simple query.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Add per-database eager and lazy meta data cache implementations - useful for schemas with auto-generated constraint names.
				Options for meta-data-cache="eager|shared-eager|lazy|shared-lazy|none".
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Create logging facade to support parameterized log messages to avoid string evaluation if message won't be logged.
				Prefer jboss-logging provider, fall back to slf4j, commons-logging, then to jdk logging.
				This removes any explicit runtime dependency on a particular logging framework.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Reverse invocation order of commit/rollback using serial transaction mode.
				The first database to acquire a row lock should be the last to commit.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro" >
				Replace deprecated JGroups channel multiplexer with shared transport.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Configuration file now specifies synchronization strategies, state manager provider, and distributable capabilities provider via identifiers instead of class names.
				Uses service loader mechanism for extensibility.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Modify configuration of balancer, dialect, durability, password codecs, and meta-data cache to use service loader mechanism for extensibility.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Copy CronExpression from Quartz code base instead of pulling in entire artifact.  HA-JDBC no longer has any required dependencies.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Support system property expansion in configuration file, via ${property} notation.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.16" date="Pending">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix unintentional configuration export during initial startup for datasource, pool-datasource, and xa-datasource configs.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				In DatabaseMetaDataSupportImpl.quote(...), use case-insensitive comparison when determining if identifier is a keyword.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2850077">
				Using non-zero fetchSize in full and differential sync strategies requires auto-commit off in PostgreSQL.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Connection.setAutoCommit(...) should use a end-transaction invocation strategy, yet still be recordable.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgrade JGroups to 2.6.12.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				If first database activation fails during auto-activate, just log failure and continue with next failed database.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.16-rc-1" date="2009-06-21">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2684746">
				Fixed NullPointerException in PreparedStatement.set/ResultSet.update stream/reader/blob/clob methods, if called with null value. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2688439">
				Only consider hashed unique indexes when finding unique constraints.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure unique constraint columns are quoted, if necessary.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2728324">
				Fix memory leak caused by batch method recording when using PreparedStatement pooling.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Optimize recording of ResultSet navigation and update methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fix recording of CallableStatement.registerOutParameter(...) methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2688421">
				Fix differential sync strategy breakage when a table contains only primary key columns.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" system="SourceForge" issue="2770743" due-to="Karl Moore">
				Determine column meta data from ResultSetMetaData instead of DatabaseMetaData.getColumns(...).
				This avoids the need for dialect specific IDENTITY column detection logic.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed StandardDialect.getIdentifierPattern(DatabaseMetaData) to require that identifiers begin with a letter.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.6.10.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to 1.2.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Quartz to 1.6.5.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.5.7.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded EasyMock to 2.5.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.9.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.15" date="2009-02-17">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed infinite loop regression in DistributableLockManager$DistributableLock.tryLock(long, TimeUnit)
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed ExceptionInInitializerError regression when creating HA-JDBC connections in Java 1.4/1.5.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.14" date="2009-02-15">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed parsing of local attribute of database, datasource, etc.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.14-rc-1" date="2009-01-25">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to 1.1.6a.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.5.6.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.2.8.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.6.7.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Quartz to 1.6.4.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded EasyMock to 2.4.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="2004105">
				Remove file list items during FileSupport.close() - rather than wait for finalization.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="2004105">
				FileSupport is no longer used for large object support and is now created/destroyed per statement, rather than per connection.
				This helps mitigate temp file build-up.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Removed references to javax.sql.CommonDataSource - this broke binary compatibility with Java 1.4/1.5 for datasource configurations.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed java 1.4 binary incompatibility with Boolean (does not yet implement Comparable) not handled by Retrotranslator.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Ben Short">
				Restore autoCommit mode to its original value at the end of synchronize(...) in each strategy.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed regression in lazy/none meta-data-cache that broke synchronization. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed misleading Spanish, French, Italian, and Portuguese translation of config-not-found message.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Store child proxies using weak references to fix potential memory leak if proxy is not closed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Remote locks in DistributableLockManager now respect lock fairness.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Startup will now also consult ha-jdbc.{0}.configuration system property when searching for configuration file.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Add HA proxying of DatabaseMetaData interface.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"" issue="2103533">
				Added net.sf.hajdbc.util.servlet.DatabaseClusterShutdownContextListener to automatically shutdown a list of database clusters scoped to a servlet context.
				The clusters to shutdown are defined in a comma delimited init parameter: ha-jdbc.clusters
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.13" date="2008-05-20">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Jason Rosenberg">
				Fixed SybaseDialect.getSimpleSQL() to query for GETDATE().
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added event handler support for activation, deactivation, and synchronization events.
				Clients can opt to be notified of such events by registering themselves as handlers using the appropriate methods on the database cluster mbean.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed close() methods of Connection, Statement, and ResultSet proxies to use driver (instead of database) write invocation strategy to prevent unnecessary creation of SQL objects (potentially triggering query execution) just to be closed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Maris Orbidans">
				Fixed exception handling in FullSynchronizationStrategy.
				Exceptions wrapped as SQLException were not getting re-thrown.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed logic in DatabaseMetaDataSupport.quote(String) to properly deal with identifier case.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed synchronization to allow schemas with auto-generated constraint names (i.e. constraint names are not uniform in all databases) to function properly when meta-data-cache="none".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug where statements created from read-only connections were not getting properly load balanced.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added explicit, Referenceable DataSource, ConnectionPoolDataSource, and XADataSource proxy implementations.
				The <![CDATA[<name>]]> element of a <![CDATA[<datasource>, <pool-datasource>, or <xa-datasource>]]> configuration can define a data source implementation class name.
				If the <![CDATA[<name>]]> element is a class name, then the subsequent <![CDATA[<property name="...">]]> elements will be interpreted as property values of the data source (e.g. serverName, portNumber, databaseName).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added missing definitions for <![CDATA[<pool-datasource>]]> and <![CDATA[<xa-datasource>]]> to DTD and XSD.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Calls to PreparedStatement.addBatch() were not being recorded and, consequently, not getting replayed when a new database is activated.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1964456">
				Fixed AcquireLockDecree to use write locks, instead of a read locks, so that database activation will block transactions on remote nodes.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 2.8.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.12" date="2008-03-18">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed case normalization in DatabaseMetaDataSupport.normalize(String, String).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NullPointerException using CallableStatement stream methods.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized Balancer implementations using copy-on-write concurrent collections.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Eliminated some unnecessary runtime reflection.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed potential deadlock when synchronization is triggered while there are open transactions.
				Refactored statement read locking to lock and unlock at transaction boundaries.
				Removed obsoleted table locking in synchronization strategies.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added ConnectionPoolDataSource and XADataSource proxies, the latter required to detect distributed transaction boundaries.
				Added necessary <![CDATA[<xa-datasource>]]> and <![CDATA[<pool-datasource>]]> configuration file elements.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Renamed net.sf.hajdbc.sql.DataSource to net.sf.hajdbc.DataSourceFactory.
				This should hopefully eliminate some confusion about its usage, as it is a javax.naming.spi.ObjectFactory and not a java.sql.DataSource implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Alejandro Domenech">
				Fixed Spanish translation of log messages.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Added linked source to javadoc.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.2.6.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.6.2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.5.0.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.11" date="2008-01-14">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced accidental use of Method.getTypeParameters() with intended Method.getParameterTypes() in AbstractInvocationHandler.
				This fixes bug where state changing methods were not recorded properly and subsequently not replayed correctly on newly activated databases.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.10" date="2008-01-08">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed CronThreadPoolExecutor to work around potential inaccuracies in java.util.Date that could cause a task to be scheduled multiple times in a single cron interval.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Connection.setReadOnly() should use DatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy instead of DriverWriteInvocationStrategy.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored invoker recording to support any JDBC method regardless of InvocationStrategy implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed replay of PreparedStatement and CallableStatement set*() methods for a newly activated database.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Cleanup logic in DatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy by splitting into TransactionalDatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy and NonTransactionalDatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Rollback TestNG to 5.6.  Version 5.7 mysteriously skipped test methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				CallableStatement does not need to parse out sequences nor identity columns, nor detect SELECT...FOR UPDATE in SQL.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed broken test cases.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.9" date="2007-12-28">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				In DatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy, acquire read locks before Balancer.all() so that a newly activated database will not miss any pending write statements.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.6.1.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.8" date="2007-11-19">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1832392" due-to="gamani">
				Fixed infinite loop in CronThreadPoolExecutor when scheduled task throws an ExecutionException.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.6.0.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.7" date="2007-11-09">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Added local="true|false" attribute to database/datasource.
				Cluster panic detection now consults this flag instead of weight to determine whether a database is local or remote.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				LocalLockManager now uses a custom semaphore-based ReadWriteLock implementation instead of ReentrantReadWriteLock.
				Removed obsolete DistributableLockAdapter hack.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized DistributableLockManager using RpcDispatcher instead VotingAdapter.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed deadlocking in DistributableLockManager when simultaneous voting occurs for he same resource from different peers.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.2.3.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.7.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.6" date="2007-10-17">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed exception handling during startup to prevent subsequent javax.management.InstanceAlreadyExistsExceptions if database cluster fails to start.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1814865">
				Fixed potential deadlocking sources and improved cpu friendliness of DistributableLockManger.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.5" date="2007-10-15">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1811698">
				Fixed bug in Dialect.getAlterSequenceSQL(...) and Dialect.getAlterIdentityColumnSQL(...) causing values > 999 to get formatted with grouping separators.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1738533">
				Added "cluster panic" detection to prevent asymmetric database deactivation during a network fragmentation when in distributable mode where databases are colocated on peer nodes.
				If HA-JDBC detects a cluster panic, the cluster is stopped.
				Manual intervention is required to resolve any consequent synchronization problems and to start the cluster.
			</action>
			<action dev="pferraro" type="remove">
				Removed obsolete JBoss jmx-console FAQ entry.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.4" date="2007-10-04">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added look-ahead and to Dialect.evaluateCurrentTime() regular expression so that it does not match CURRENT_TIMESTAMP functions.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NullPointerException regression in DistributableLockManager preventing database activation in distributable mode.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Use new official JDK 1.4 backport of JGroups instead of retrotranslating our own.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.3" date="2007-09-24">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.5.1.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1799618">
				Fixed infinite loop in DistributableLockManager while acquiring a lock when only one peer node is present.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed missing membership listener registration in DistributableLockManager preventing proper lock cleanup.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1796975">
				Defer creation of connection factories until needed since DataSource creation relies on JNDI environment properties that may not yet be established.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.2" date="2007-09-14">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added Dialect.getIdentifierPattern(...) method to work around buggy DatabaseMetaData.getExtraNameCharacters() in PostgreSQL driver since version 8.1.
				Bug causes unexpected failures during identity column detection when schema or table name contains non-standard characters.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized StandardDialect.getDefaultSchemas() by replacing separate CURRENT_USER query with DatabaseMetaData.getUserName().
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed example Tomcat DataSource configuration.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed currentTimestampFunction() method of MaxDBDialect.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Created separate OracleDialect, formerly an alias of MaxDBDialect.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Created separate H2Dialect, formerly an alias of HSQLDBDialect.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added new dialect for Sybase.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added evaluateCurrentDate(String, java.sql.Date), evaluateCurrentTime(String, java.sql.Time), evaluateCurrentTimestamp(String, java.sql.Timestamp), and evaluateRandom(String) to Dialect interface to replace non-deterministic SQL functions (e.g. CURRENT_TIMESTAMP, RAND()) with deterministic static values.
				Added optional eval-current-date, eval-current-time, eval-current-timestamp, and eval-rand cluster attribute to enable these behaviors.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Both sequence and identity column detection are no longer enabled by default.
			</action>
			<action dev="pferraro" type="remove">
				Removed supportsSequences() and supportsIdentityColumns() methods from Dialect interface.
				The corresponding parseSequence(String) and parseInsertTable(String) methods now return null for dialects that do not support these features.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed race condition in DistributableLockAdapter that may prevent a lock from being released.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.4.3.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added SynchronizationSupport.synchronizeIdentityColumns(...).
				Consequently, MySQL AUTO_INCREMENT columns are now fully supported.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro"">
				Added DatabaseProperties.getSequences() and TableProperties.getIdentityColumns() to meta data cache facility.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.1" date="2007-07-23">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				LazyDatabaseMetaDataCache now caches DatabaseProperties using a SoftReference to prevent the cache from causing OutOfMemoryErrors.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored ThreadLocalDatabaseMetaDataCache to NullDatabaseMetaDataCache which no long stores its DatabaseProperties instance in a ThreadLocal since this can inadvertently act like a lazy cache if application threads are pooled.
				Replaced SynchronizationContext.getDatabaseMetaDataCache() with SynchronizationContext.getDatabaseProperties() so that meta data used during synchronization is still cached for the lifetime of the SynchronizationContext, regardless of cache implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Re-implemented BalancerFactory, DialectFactory, and DatabaseMetaDataCacheFactory using enums.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				In DatabaseMetaDataSupport.normalize(...), adjust case of table to match the way identifiers are stored in the database.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				In DatabaseMetaDataSupport.quote(...), normalize identifiers to lower case if database is case-insensitive, yet stores identifiers in mixed case.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed all benign compiler warnings reported by Eclipse.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated simple string constants to Strings.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0.0" date="2007-07-16">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized failure handling in DatabaseWriteInvocationStrategy.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized thread synchronization in DistributableLockAdapter.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded EasyMock to 2.3.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.4.2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.5 GA.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Revised documentation.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-rc-4" date="2007-07-07">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				In distributable mode, try to retrieve initial state from any remote node, not just "coordinator".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed deadlocking during activation/deactivation in distributable mode caused by redundant secondary notifications.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				In distributable mode, do not send activation notifications to other nodes during cluster startup.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				In distributable mode, do not respond to initial state queries until cluster startup is complete.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.4.1.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-rc-3" date="2007-07-02">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				FailureDetectionTask and SQLProxy.handleFailure() will not deactivate any databases if they all appear to be dead.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Convert dynamic Class.cast() and Class.isInstance() to static cast and instanceof expressions wherever possible.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug during initialization where databases are added as dirty, triggering export of configuration file.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				When adding a database to the cluster, perform duplicate id check before registering database to avoid InstanceAlreadyExistsException.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed broken error message when attempting to remove a database that is still active.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-rc-2" date="2007-06-25">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added toString() to DatabaseClusterMBean interface so that log messages will display cluster id properly.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="David White">
				Fixed IllegalAccessError in JiBX marshalling during configuration export.n
			</action>
			<action dev="pferraro" type="remove">
				Removed Retrotranslator plugin for java.lang.management.ManagementFactory.
				This is now natively supported by Retrotranslator.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.2.2.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-rc-1" date="2007-06-18">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed memory leak with CONCUR_READ_ONLY result sets when using ResultSet.getStatement().close().
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Removed problematic singleton references to database clusters in DatabaseClusterFactory.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Require separate XML config file per database cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Consolidated database-cluster and datasource cluster elements into single cluster element, as in 1.1.
				Removed id attribute from cluster element.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Modified configuration locator logic to first check driver connection properties or datasource config property for resource URL.
				Default resource name is now ha-jdbc-{0}.xml, where {0} is the cluster id.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Hanson Char">
				Added test for UnsupportedOperationException thrown when Quartz cron expression uses both day-of-week and day-of-month values.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				If a group member leaves, any distributed locks it held must be freed.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				DistributableLockManager uses default vote response processor instead of its own implementation.
			</action>
			<action dev="pferraro" type="remove">
				Removed quoting of cluster ID and database ID in mbean ObjectName.
				JBoss users no longer need to patiently wait for this long standing jmx-console bug (http://jira.jboss.com/jira/browse/JBAS-2037) to be fixed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NoSuchElementException thrown during database activation when there are no active databases.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed IllegalMonitorStateExceptions in DistributableLockManager resulting from improper use of reentrant locks by multiple threads.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized DistributableLockManager using a single phase VotingAdapter.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Re-implemented DistributableStateManager to use synchronous MessageDispatcher instead of asynchronous NotificationBus.
				This will ensure that all nodes are notified of database activation prior to unlocking database tables during synchronization.
				Changed default jgroups protocol stack to "udp-sync".
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Do not auto-deactivate the last database of a cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				JGroups 2.5 uses Java 1.5 as a baseline, so retrotranslate this jar as part of 1.4 build.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Modified build to produce 3 different binary distributions, for Java 1.4, 1.5, and 1.6.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.4.0.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to 1.1.5.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.5.0-cr1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.6.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="2.0-beta-1" date="2007-04-23">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="David Goodenough">
				Optimized PostgreSQLDialect.getLockTableSQL() by removing unnecessary select statement.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Removed JVM shutdown hook since it may prevent proper shutdown of a server-managed connection pool.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1618746">
				Fixed NullPointerException accessing meta data if database does not support schemas.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored Balancer.list() to return a set to better reflect balancer semantics.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored DatabaseClusterMBean interface into DriverDatabaseClusterMBean and DataSourceDatabaseClusterMBean.
				LocalDatabaseCluster refactored into generic AbstractDatabaseCluster.
				Replaced &lt;cluster&gt; element in DTD with &lt;database-cluster&gt; and &lt;datasource-cluster&gt;.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Created StateManager to encapsulate management of database cluster state.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Distributable functionality no longer added via inheritance, but through lock manager and state manager implementations.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Created schema definition of HA-JDBC configuration as an alternative to DTD.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Reimplemented core logic to use dynamic instead of explicit proxies, decoupling HA-JDBC from a specific version of the JDBC API.
				Resulting jar is approximately half the size as before.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored SynchronousExecutor implementation to extend AbstractExecutorService since the ExecutorService interface in Java 1.6 is not compatible with that of 1.5.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Java 1.6 adds auto-increment column identification to DatabaseMetaData.getColumns().
				Added isAutoIncrement() to ColumnProperties interface populated only if this information exists.
				This value is now be consulted prior to querying the dialect to identify identity columns.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed regular expressions in dialects to properly negotiate whitespace.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added support for JDBC 4.0 (i.e. Java 1.6).
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added support for mutable LOBs.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added Java 1.6 service provider hook for HA-JDBC driver.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added max batch size property to differential synchronization strategy to help prevent out of memory errors when a table contains many changes.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Use platform mbean server for cluster/database mbean registration.
				Provide retrotranslator plugin for java.lang.management.ManagementFactory that uses old logic to locate mbean server.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Forced cleanup of open java.sql objects that were not accessed during an deactivate/reactivate cycle.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Kurt Huwig">
				Fixed german message transations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to 1.1.3.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.5.0-beta-2.
				concurrent-*.jar is now obsolete.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.3.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.2.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Woodstox to 3.2.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.5.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added JDBC RowSet API to Java 1.4 runtime dependencies.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Updated documentation to use Forrest 0.8.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-7" date="2006-12-01">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed sequence synchronization logic to use next value instead of current value since it may be undefined.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored SynchronizationStrategy interface into distinct prepare (e.g. lock), synchronize, and cleanup (e.g. unlock) stages.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Created SynchronizationContext to simplify SynchronizationStrategy interface methods.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored CronExecutorService to use CronExpression instead of CronTrigger.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed default distributable stack to "udp".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Disabled support for identity columns in MySQL dialect.
				MySQL's implementation has no mechanism to synchronize auto-increment counter.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.4 GA (final).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.1.0.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Quartz to 1.6.0.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Woodstox to 3.1.0.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to 1.1.0 RC1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.3.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-6" date="2006-10-24">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added support for identity columns.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added new cluster attributes "detect-sequences" and "detect-identity-columns".
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added dialect implementations for Ingres and Mckoi.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Woodstox to 3.0.2.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed PostgreSQL Blob/Clob handling in differential and full synchronization strategies when large objects require updating.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored DefaultDialect to StandardDialect and renamed dialect alias from "default" to "standard".
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-5" date="2006-09-22">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.2.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed binding compilation error that only seemed to affect windows users.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed mbean registration race condition during startup in distributable mode.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-4" date="2006-09-11">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.4-cr-2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Woodstox to 3.0.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.1.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" issue="1543962">
				Force cleanup of underlying connections, statements, and result sets when a database is deactivated.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Log cause of DatabaseCluster.isAlive(Database) failures.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in DatabaseMetaDataSupport.getForeignKeyConstraints() causing method to always return an empty collection.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in PostgreSQLDialect.getSequences(...) causing method to fail to when database does not contain any sequences.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-3" date="2006-08-26">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy where generated select statements had duplicated columns.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Extracted interfaces from ColumnProperties, ForeignKeyConstraint, and UniqueConstraint.
				Implementations refactored into net.sf.hajdbc.cache package.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added long needed unit tests for each synchronization strategy.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to 2.4-cr-1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to 1.0.8.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Stephan Hesse">
				Fixed bugs in MySQLDialect related to generating SQL for creating and dropping foreign keys and unique constraints.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-2" date="2006-08-10">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 5.0.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Woodstox to 3.0.0.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed premature quoting of schema and tables in DatabaseMetaDataCacheSupport.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NullPointerException in ThreadLocalDatabaseMetaDataCache.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in SimpleBalancer where a database deactivation would trigger the deactivation of other databases of identical weight.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.2-beta-1" date="2006-07-19">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to version 1.0.7.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to version 1.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced XMLPull runtime library with StAX API + Woodstox implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to version 2.3-sp1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded SLF4J to version 1.0.2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Quartz to version 1.5.2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded EasyMock to version 2.2.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to version 5.0.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Ryan Holmes">
				Fixed create/drop constraint methods of DefaultDialect to quote constraint names.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Modified Dialect interface to leverage ForeignKeyConstraint and UniqueConstraint objects to encapsulate constraint details.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed DefaultDialect to correctly generate create foreign key statements for foreign keys containing multiple columns, ON DELETE/UPDATE actions, and deferrability.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Created dialects for MySQL and Firebird.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				DerbyDialect, HSQLDBDialect, MaxDBDialect now override createForeignKeySQL().
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed synchronization of PostgreSQL tables containing Blob (oid) columns.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Modified differential synchronization strategy to use UPDATE statements instead of using updatable ResultSet, due to poor driver support.
				e.g. ResultSet.updateBlob(...) is not implemented in PostgreSQL driver.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added DatabaseMetaData caching.  New meta-data-cache attribute of cluster.  Options are eager, lazy, or none.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Modified Dialect and SynchronizationStrategy interfaces to use DatabaseMetaDataCache objects.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored Dialect interface with much simpler method signatures.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Leverages JGroups 2.3 multiplexing so that notification bus and distributable lock manager share the same channel.
				No more "discarded message from different group..." warnings in logs!
				"protocol" attribute of "distributable" element in DTD is replaced by "config" and "stack" attributes.
				Default for "config" is "stacks.xml" from JGroups distribution.  Default for "stack" is "fc-fast-minimalthreads".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Moved mbean registration to DatabaseCluster.start() and added mbean unregistration to DatabaseCluster.stop().
				HA-JDBC initialization failures will no longer leave stray registered mbeans.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced simple read-write locking with named read-write locking encapsulated by a LockManager.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added support for sequences.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored unit tests so that test classes implement subject interfaces.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed non-default charset handling of Clobs.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1" date="2006-04-21">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Ensure that causes of initialization failures are logged.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-rc-2" date="2006-04-18">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed IllegalArgumentException during startup when using transactions="xa".
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NullPointerException during startup when database does not define a driver.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed CronExecutorService to use daemon threads so that it doesn't prevent the shutdown hook from firing.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-rc-1" date="2006-04-09">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to version 1.0.3.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed Blob/Clob handling in PreparedStatement.setBlob(...)/setBlob(...) and ResultSet.updateBlob(...)/updateClob(...) methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in DefaultDialect.qualifyTable(...) for databases that do not support schemas.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added new required transactions="local|xa" option to cluster.
				When in local mode, database writes are performed concurrently.
				When in xa mode, database writes are performed synchronously to ensure a predictable execution order and prevent deadlocks.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added fault tolerance measures to cluster thread pool under high load.
				If pool size reaches max-threads threshold, database writes will be executed in the caller thread using java.util.concurrent.ThreadPoolExecutor.CallerRunsPolicy.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded TestNG to 4.7.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-7" date="2006-03-20">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro" due-to="Tapan Paul">
				Added auto-activate-period cluster option that will auto-activate failed database nodes at a configurable interval.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				New dependency on Quartz (http://opensymphony.com/quartz/).
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Created CronThreadPoolExecutor, a java.util.concurrent.ThreadPoolExecutor that leverages a Quartz CronTrigger to calculate future execution times of a scheduled task.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Enhanced auto-activation and failure detection to use a cron schedule, instead of a simple fixed-delay period.
				Renamed failure-detect-period to failure-detect-schedule and auto-activate-period to auto-activate-schedule in DTD.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated repository to Subversion.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated test suite to TestNG.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated logging facade from commons-logging to SLF4J.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				New dependency on SLF4J (http://slf4j.org).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to version 1.0.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced commons-logging-1.0.4.jar with jcl104-over-slf4j.jar from SLF4J distribution.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added management interface methods for adding and removing databases from a cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Separated DatabaseMBean interface into InactiveDatabaseMBean (read-write) and ActiveDatabaseMBean (read-only).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Activating/Deactivating database reregisters the database using the appropriate active/inactive mbean interface.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added dirty flag logic for Database attributes.  If a database is dirty when it is activated, then the HA-JDBC configuration is exported.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Renamed "name" property of DataSource to "cluster", since "name" cannot be set by the BeanFactory from Tomcat's server.xml file.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Revised main documentation.  Added more FAQs.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-6" date="2006-02-15">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added workaround for missing ReentrantReadWriteLock(boolean) constructor in backport-util-concurrent package.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Added verify flag to retrotranslator compilation to catch future Java 1.4 compatibility issues.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Rollback change to PostgreSQL dialect.
				Removed batching of lock table commands.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-5" date="2006-02-13">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Database activation uses Lock.lockInterruptibly() instead of Lock.tryLock() to prevent activation from failing due to concurrent writes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed getLockTableSQL() from PostgreSQL dialect so that it can be executed within a batch.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-4" date="2006-02-10">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Retrotranslator to version 0.9.8.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added optional failure-detect-period to configuration file.
				If defined, HA-JDBC will proactively detect database failures every specified number of seconds.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Replace DatabaseCluster.init() with start() and stop() methods.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added JVM shutdown hook that calls stop() on each DatabaseCluster.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro" due-to="Kurt Huwig">
				Derby dialect overrides getLockTableSQL().
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored DistributableDatabaseCluster to extend LocalDatabaseCluster rather than contain/decorate it.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored JiBX configuration to support both input and output binding directions.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Removed configuration related methods from SynchronizationStrategy interface removing the need for AbstractSynchronizationStrategy.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Implemented distributable read-write locking so that database writes are locked during database activation.
				This eliminates the need to deactivate databases that were newly actived upon completion of a database write.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added mbean interfaces for Databases.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-3" date="2006-01-27">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed exceptions thrown by DatabaseClusterMBean methods to built-in Java exceptions so that they can be interpretted by a remote JMX client.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added distributable locking to prevent multiple simultaneous synchronizations on the same cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added configurable timeout attribute to DTD for distributable operations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Moved SELECT ... FOR UPDATE pattern definition to dialect.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed IndexOutOfBoundsException during database activation when one or more databases in the cluster is not alive.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-2" date="2006-01-23">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to version 1.0.1.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to version 2.2.9.1.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Ilkka Lassila">
				Recorded Operations are stored in a Map keyed by class instead of a List to prevent unnecessary boundless growth.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Kurt Huwig">
				DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy generates bad DELETE statements when table has multiple primary keys.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Kurt Huwig">
				Fixes german error message translations.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				DatabaseClusterFactory.createDatabaseClusterFactory() throws RuntimeException instead of SQLException to prevent java.sql.DriverManager from masking root cause of HA-JDBC configuration failures.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixes potential NullPointerException if database is deactivated as a result of a read operation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated code base to Java 1.5.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Retrotranslator (http://retrotranslator.sf.net) leveraged for JDK 1.4 compatibility.
				Build script generates separate 1.4 jar and includes additional dependencies.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced Balancer.toArray() : Database[] with Balancer.list() : List<![CDATA[<Database>]]>
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Unit tests now use EasyMock 2.0.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added requiresTableLocking() method to SynchronizationStrategy interface.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				During database activation, table locking is only performed if required by synchronization strategy.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				All vendor specific customizations to HA-JDBC are now encompassed in the Dialect attribute of a cluster.
				This replaces the validate-sql attribute of a cluster; and the truncateTableSQL, createForeignKeySQL, dropForeignKeySQL, createUniqueKeySQL, and dropUniqueKeySQL properties of the diff and full synchronization strategies.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Created dialects for PostgreSQL, MaxDB, Derby, HSQLDB, and a default dialect.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Changed default table locking query used during synchronization to use an innocuous UPDATE statement.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added more explicit logging for exceptions thrown during HA-JDBC initialization that end up getting masked by JiBX.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Kurt Huwig">
				Added missing rollback to exception handling in diff and full synchronization strategies.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				In distributable mode, JGroups channel and protocols are registed with the mbean server.
			</action>
			<action type="remove" dev="pferraro">
				Removed obsolete net.sf.hajdbc.sql.pool.xa and net.sf.hajdbc.sql.pool packages.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.1-beta-1" date="2005-12-13">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				New dependency on JDK 1.4 backport of JDK 1.5 java.util.concurrent package.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Uses configurable thread pooling for asynchronously executed write operations for improved efficiency and fault tolerance under high load.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Uses default-minimalthreads.xml from JGroups distribution as default distributable protocol.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Synchronization strategies now use schema qualified table names when appropriate.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to version 2.2.9.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed problematic co-dependency between DatabaseCluster and ConnectionFactory.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0" date="2005-09-22">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Roman Kurmanowytsch">
				Fixed JDK 1.4 source compatibility issues.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added explicit logging to expose root causes of exceptions that are hidden by JiBX.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added FAQ section for manually deleting local cluster state.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added FAQ section for distinguishing application database users vs. HA-JDBC database users.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded EasyMock to version 1.2.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-rc-5" date="2005-09-15">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				During DatabaseClusterFactory initialization, if no mbean server can be found, an exception is thrown, rather than attempting to create a new one.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Quote all identifiers used in synchronization to prevent SQL syntax errors in identifier is a reserved word.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-rc-4" date="2005-09-06">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Nick Rudnick">
				Correct error message when connection to config url fails.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Avoid wrapping SQLException cause when a database operation fails.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added FAQ section for running HA-JDBC under Tomcat 5.0.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Matthew Wooller">
				Fixed readProperties() and writeProperties(...) methods of AbstractSynchronizationStrategy to ignore the property "class".
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Reintroduced PassiveSynchronizationStrategy.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Added logic to LocalDatabaseCluster.loadState() to validate locally persisted cluster state.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-rc-3" date="2005-08-23">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed NullPointerException bug in LocalDatabaseCluster.loadState().
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Distributable database activation commands should not reinvoke synchronization.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-rc-2" date="2005-08-21">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				SELECT...FOR UPDATE queries are now detected and distributed to each database cluster node.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Nick Rudnick">
				Corrected German translation of error messages.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed infinite loop in AbstractSynchronizationStrategy.getProperties().
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in LocalDatabaseCluster.loadState() when cluster is empty.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-rc-1" date="2005-08-02">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored HA-JDBC initialization and DTD.  Synchronization strategies are now shared across all clusters.  Each cluster defines a default synchronization strategy.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added properties to cluster configuration to allow DataSources to define custom JNDI environment parameters and to allow Driver to define additional runtime parameters.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed default JGroups protocol stack to use FD instead of FD_SOCK.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				activate(String) method in DatabaseClusterMBean interface will synchronize using the default synchronization strategy for the cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Removed getSynchronizationStrategies() from DatabaseClusterMBean interface.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed ClassCastException during XADataSource initialization.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				SQLException wrapper properly reports vendor-specific error code and SQL state.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Updated DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy to use PreparedStatements for inserts and deletions instead of using problematic updatable result set methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy to drop and re-create unique keys on each table to prevent possible unique constraint violations during sync.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy now correctly compares byte[] columns.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Migrated unit tests from TestNG to JUnit in order to utilize EasyMock.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added unit tests for net.sf.hajdbc.sql package.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Forrest documentation to version 0.7.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to version 2.2.8.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to version 1.0-rc-1.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-8" date="2005-04-27">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Cluster state is now persisted locally so that it can be restored between application restarts.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added customizable fetchSize property to each synchronization strategy to avoid out of memory errors when synchronizing large tables.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added TestNG unit tests for Driver, Connection, Statement, and each balancer implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed issue with driver returning non-distributable connections when in distributable mode.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed issue in DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy with some updatable result set implementations where inserted rows were deleted again.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed ClassCastException in Connection.releaseSavepoint(Savepoint) and Connection.rollback(Savepoint) methods.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Minor fixes to zero weight handling in random and load balancers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro" due-to="Oezcan Acar">
				Corrected German translation of error messages.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				executeWriteToDatabase() will now throw SQLException for Statements and ResultSets if some valid databases fail while others succeed and auto-commit is off, giving the client the opportunity to rollback the current transaction.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Connection.isReadOnly() was changed from executeReadFromDatabase() to executeReadFromDriver().
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored java.sql.* proxy classes.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JiBX to version 1.0-rc-0.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-7" date="2005-04-05">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed buggy weighted round-robin algorithm.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Round-robin balancer now handles databases with 0 weight properly.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-6" date="2005-03-31">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Database cluster now specifies 1 of 4 different strategies for balancing read requests: simple, random, round-robin, or load.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				A database can define a weight to affect how it is prioritized by the balancer.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				In distributed environment, a database cluster will get its initial state from the JGroups group coordinator.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug where auto (i.e. non-manual) database deactivation behaved locally even if environment is distributed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug where synchronization strategies will fail if foreign key constraints have names that require quoting (e.g. $1, $2).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Lots of refactored code.  Most notably, the HA-JDBC driver has moved to net.sf.hajdbc.sql.Driver
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Protocol parameter is now optional for distributable clusters.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro" due-to="AltaVista Babel Fish">
				Added error message translations for German, Spanish, French, Italian, and Portuguese.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added error message for tables without primary keys in DifferentialSynchronizationStrategy.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-5" date="2005-03-03">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Added better data type support for SynchronizationStrategy properties.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed Java 1.4 compatibility.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-4" date="2005-02-18">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				getActiveDatabases() and getInactiveDatabases() no longer throw SQLException
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Configuration DTD updated:  Synchronization strategies and properties are now explicitly defined per cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added getSynchronizationStrategies() method to cluster management interface.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed symantics of activate(...) methods on management interface:  activate(String, String) uses synchronization strategy identifier instead of class name; activate(String) now activates a database without synchronizing.
			</action>
			<action type="remove" dev="pferraro">
				PassiveSynchronizationStrategy is obsolete.  Use activate(String) instead.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				synchronize() method of SynchronizationStrategy interface no longer uses DatabaseClusterDescriptor.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed various bugs in documentation and javadoc.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-3" date="2005-02-07">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				All log/exception messages are now localized.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Driver is no longer required when defining a driver-based cluster since underlying driver already be registered via the jdbc.drivers system property.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in SQLException when nested exception chain is already initialized.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-2" date="2005-01-08">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added JMX interface to DatabaseCluster to allow administration of each cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored cluster initialization and management.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Distributable behavior implemented using command pattern.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Restructured configuration DTD adding new synchronization-related cluster properties.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored distributable behavior to support activation.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added ability to activate a failed database.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Created database synchronization strategies used during activation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Allow simple names for DriverManager-based database cluster.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Enhanced large object support.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded Forrest documentation to v0.6.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-beta-1" date="2004-10-01">
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in connection.rollback()
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed logic in PreparedStatement/CallableStatement.setXXXStream() and ResultSet.updateXXXStream() methods
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Optimized asynchronous execution of write operations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Improved consistancy of cluster when autocommit is true.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to v2.2.7
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Prevent multiple logging of database deactivation
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-alpha-3" date="2004-08-30">
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Configuration DTD is now PUBLIC
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Upgraded JGroups to v2.2.6
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed thread safety bug in SQLProxy.executeWrite()
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Changed license to LGPL, added license details to source code
			</action>
			<action type="remove" dev="pferraro">
				Removed obsolete RowSetProxy class, javax.sql.RowSet implementation are implicitly supported
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Refactored package names to reflect project name
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Replaced CHANGES.txt with this page
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-alpha-2" date="2004-07-17">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Added ability specify location of configuration file using a system property
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				Extended classpath search for configuration file to include system classpath
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed DataSource proxy initialization
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="pferraro">
				DriverProxy now expects the cluster name to match the JDBC url
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Several refactorings affecting configuration dtd
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="pferraro">
				Fixed bug in clean target of ant build file
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.0-alpha-1" date="2004-07-14">
			<action type="add" dev="pferraro">
				Initial Release
			</action>
		</release>
	</body>
</document>
